<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A secure and prudent choice of beliefe. Written by a student in diuinity</title>
            <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850086</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850086</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15270</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15270)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1271:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A secure and prudent choice of beliefe. Written by a student in diuinity</title>
                  <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M. DC. XXXIX [1639]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Floyd.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Society of Jesus Library, Mount Street.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15270:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15270:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SECVRE AND PRVDENT CHOICE <hi>of Beliefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by a Student in Diuinity.</p>
            <p>Anno M.DC.XXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15270:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15270:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OTHING in this world doth more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a Man for his good, both temporall and eternall, then the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. What more confeſſed amongſt Chriſtians not infected with Atheiſme? yet ſuch is our poore Condition, that nothing ordinarily is leſſe valued: many ſtubbornly retayning what they haue beene taught from their youth; Others embracing what is moſt commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where they liue; Others indifferent, meerely Animals, their wits ſeruing them no further then how to haue good dayes; Others, loath to take paines, leaſt thereby their Conſcience be moued to Croſſe their couetous appetites; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with a kind of frenzy, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15270:3"/>themſelues of I know not what Ghoſt: Others, lurking vnder affected &amp; willfull ignorance, perſwaded they are vncapable of their right leuell in theſe troubled waters: Multitudes fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, apprehending little difference in points of Religion, ſleepe ſecurely vpon any pillow. Many of theſe, though of different beleifes, flatter themſelues with hope of ſaluation, when they haue little reaſon to be ſecure thereof; as it will appeare by the infallible rule of a <hi>Secure Choice</hi> I will propoſe in this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe: For which purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſuppoſe firſt, that our Bleſſed Sauiour, when he was to depart in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible preſence from this world, his laſt care was to leaue his Church prouided with ſuch as ſhould ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly gouerne, teach, and augment it after him, to whom &amp; their Succeſſors for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he promiſed his eſpeciall aſſiſtance and protection to the end of the world: <hi>As my Father hath ſent me, ſo I ſend you. Io.</hi> 20.21. <hi>Going into the whole world, preach the Goſpell. Marke</hi> 16. Heere we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15270:3"/>ſee the Apoſtles Commiſſion, not only to go as being ſent, but alſo to ſend o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their Succeſſours with the like authority to be ſucceſſiuely deliuered. That alſo he left ample power for the perfect gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſame Church, beſides theſe places, that of <hi>S. Matth.</hi> 28. deſerueth ſpeciall Conſideration: <hi>All power is giuen me in heauen, and in earth; going therefore, teach all Nations.</hi> Where that illation, <hi>Going therefore,</hi> implieth a moſt ample authority for hauing ſaid all power is giuen me, he preſently pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctizeth and giueth the like, ſaying <hi>going therefore.</hi> Moreouer that we may know nothing ſhould be wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting to the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gouernment of this his Church, and that iuſtly it may be eſteemed to be directed, not ſo much by humane wit or induſtry, as by the ſpirit of God; he promiſed <hi>Io.</hi> 14. <hi>And I will pray my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he will giue you another Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he may abide with you for euer, the Spirit of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It cannot be denied, but theſe places enforce an eminent, perpetuall,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15270:4"/>and infallible Authority of Chriſtes Church, to which ſuch ample power is giuen, &amp; where the ſpirit of truth is promiſed to reſide. Yet becauſe meanes are found to delude the force of them (as of any others there may be) I inſiſt not vpon them, but for the preſent only make this <hi>Dilemma:</hi> Either theſe Texts are cleerly to be vnderſtood as they lye, or not: if they are; then there hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene a perpetuall, abſolute, and infallible power of gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the Church of chriſt eſtabliſhed. If not, this only I will gather, as out of other Texts it may be, that ſcarce any can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſo cleere for the proofe of any verity, which may not maliciouſly be wreſted to a ſtrange ſenſe, by tongues ſounding nothing more ſacredly then Scripture. Thus all Sectaries, though contrary amongſt themſelues, auouch for their vndoubted warrant, Holy Scripture, ſome vnderſtanding it in one ſenſe, others in an other: when indeed the proofe is not out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but out of their owne priuate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15270:4"/>iudgment. Who then doth not ſee, how vainely Scripture only, is pretended for warrant of their contrary inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and how hard it is to conuince the truth by it alone? not for that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth not all truth, and all ſufficient inſtruction for ſaluation, but becauſe following our owne priuate iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we may erre in the ſenſe therof. Since therefore no man, though of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo entire iudgment, can ſufficiently ſhew his owne ſenſe to be true and the contrary falſe, as it appeareth by ſuch monſtrous Contradictions vpon the ſame Texts; it is euident, that from Scripture alone, we can promiſe our ſelues little, or no ſecurity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Secondly, I ſuppoſe there is a Church of Chriſt extant, that beareth the true markes of his promiſes and prouidence; renowned for antiquity and continued Succeſſion; perſpicious for extent; knit in vnity; adorned with vnanimous Conſent of Doctours throughout the world; eſtabliſhed and maintained by Councels; beautifyed &amp;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15270:5"/>enriched with multitudes of holy men, admirable for their Conuerſation and vertue; ſtrengthned with miracles; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in Doctrine and Cuſtome profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing piety, that any one beholding it may ſay, heere is the finger of God, this is the light, this the hill on the topp of hills.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thirdly I ſuppoſe what truth it ſelfe (Marc. 16.) denounceth; <hi>He that will not belieue, ſhall be damned.</hi> Whence vnder paine of Damnation we are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged not to disbelieue any point pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vnto vs in holy Scripture; for Chriſt ſpecified not any particular ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle or articles, but to all disbeliefe of his Goſpell he denounceth Damnation, <hi>Going into all the world, preach the Goſpell, he that will not belieue &amp;c.</hi> Hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that amongſt different opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s concerning the ſame Scripture, that part is leſſe ſecure, that denieth the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles propoſed out of it, ſince for disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife Damnation is denounced, not for beleife.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fourthly, I ſuppoſe as conſequent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15270:5"/>to what is ſaid, that if an article com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly belieued, be iudged hard by any priuate man, it is not ſecure for him to condemne it, relying only vpon human diſcourſe, though ioined with his owne or ſome others interpretation of holy Scripture, for all this is but in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of probability, and not different from the meanes the <hi>Arians,</hi> and other impious heretiques vſed; conſequently vnſufficient to diſproue the contrary poſſeſſed beliefe, though it be but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed probable: but he muſt produce cleere Scripture without addition, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution, ſuppoſition, or interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſince theſe are ſubiect to doubt, &amp; conſequently to danger of leading into disbeliefe; who doth not ſee how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible this is?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Finally, for the end of this prudent Choyce, I ſuppoſe, as ſufficient, in that religion which firſt belieueth many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, denied afterwards by others, a moral probability of the ſenſe of Chriſts word: and this no wiſe man can deny to a Church ancient, and conſiſting of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15270:6"/>Councels and learned men in all parts of the world: agreeing in one opinion without any alteration euidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. To ſay that any article is improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe it is impoſſible, is to proue by a ground not poſſible to be proued, and to ouerthrow all fayth, as is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt. We ſeeke not then what ſeemeth poſſible or impoſſible to our poore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, but what moſt probably Chriſt deliuered: and he that with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities only denieth what is but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably belieued, is not in ſecure ſtate of his ſaluation.</p>
            <p n="7">7. By theſe grounds cleere inough in themſelues, euery Chriſtian may eaſily diſcerne what Religion is ſecure in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, to wit, that which remoueth him furtheſt from danger of that ſentence, <hi>Who will not belieue shalbe damned.</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Touchſtone for the better inſtruction of the common ſort, I will examin the chiefe points now in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, that by theſe examples the reſt may be eaſily examined.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15270:6"/>
               <head>What Choice ought a man to make concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Real Preſence of Christs body and bloud in the Sacrament of the last Supper.</head>
               <p n="8">8. TO iuſtify the beliefe thereof, we haue firſt the words of Chriſt, <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6. where he amply promiſeth his body and bloud: <hi>My flesh is truly meate, and my blood &amp;c. he that eateth my flesh &amp;c.</hi> he that will not belieue this, but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it in a different ſenſe from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, perſuaded by thoſe obſcure words, <hi>the ſpirit giueth life, the flesh profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing,</hi> expoſeth him to danger of disbeliefe with the Iewes, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, ſince <hi>Verſ.</hi> 56. it is ſaid: <hi>he that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my flesh, and drinketh my blood, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in me, and I in him.</hi> And S Paul to the Col. c. 1. <hi>You which were in times past stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and enemies</hi> &amp;c. <hi>hath he now reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the body of his flesh through death to make you holy;</hi> how then can thoſe words, <hi>the flesh profiteth nothing</hi> without danger be vnderſtood of the fleſh of Chriſt as profiting nothing? is it not profit to vs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15270:7"/>that Chriſt ſhould dwell in vs, and we in him? that we are reconciled in the body of his fleſh?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Secondly, the words of Chriſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming: <hi>This is my body; take and eate; do this</hi> &amp;c. which words if we wreſt to a figuratiue ſenſe, we muſt bring cleere Scripture for it, elſe our interpretation is dangerous, denying ſuch a cleere my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery vpon human motiues. Thirdly, we haue the teſtimony of <hi>S. Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. If theſe places be obſcure, we haue beſides the Conſent of Nations, the common voyce of the whole Chriſtian world for a thouſand fiue hundred yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res without Contradiction. Finally, in the beliefe and practiſe thereof, there is no impiety, but prayſe and honour of Chriſt, who vpon ſufficient grounds is ſuppoſed preſent vnder the formes of bread and wine; he is receiued with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, the ſoule being firſt prepared with harty ſorrow for ſinnes paſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with loue, thankfulnes, and liuely remembrance of his ſacred Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp;c. For deniall of this beliefe we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15270:7"/>haue but ſmall authority, not one cleere teſtimony of Scripture that interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thoſe words of Chriſt as figurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely ſpoken, all other arguments can be but probable.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Now I aske any indifferent mans iudgment, what he would do, in caſe a perfect figure of Chriſt ſhould viſibly appeare, commonly acknowledged and worſhipped by all with ſincere inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If furthermore it were deliuered commonly, that to ſuſpect the appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as an illuſion of Sathan, were a wrong to Chriſt; will he aduenture to ſpit at it? will he not rather forbeare that, and iudge it ſecure to belieue and worſhip with others, ſince therein he findeth no hurt, but inuincible motiues to do ſo? Cleere then it is, what we ought to reſolue in this point, ſince for the beliefe we haue inuincible motiues; in the practiſe there is no danger of any impiety, as certainly there is in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, if we grant but probability in the beliefe.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Only it may be obiected, that if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15270:8"/>Chriſt be not vnder thoſe formes of bread and wine, there is danger of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. But this is a manifeſt miſtake; for Belieuers adore not bread nor wine, nor any Creature, but Chriſt, whom vpon good grounds they ſuppoſe preſent ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally. Know therefore, that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration conſiſteth of outward reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ioyned with interiour, as of body and ſoule: the outward is indifferent to God and Creatures, the interiour ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it makes the difference. Exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour reuerence applied by our inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a temporall Lord is but a Ciuil worſhip: the ſame applied by our inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a Saint, as a Creature of God highly in his fauour, is a higher degree of honour, yet within the limits of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour worſhip. It is likewiſe applied by our intention to God our Creatour and Sauiour, thus it is perfect adoration and due only to God. He then that belieueth Chriſt is conteyned ſacramentally vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the formes of bread and wine may ſecurely adore, ſince his adoration pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from his beliefe, transferreth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15270:8"/>the outward act from all Creatures, &amp; directeth it to God himſelfe, euen in caſe in his immediate beliefe he ſhould be miſtaken; there remayneth then no da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in the beliefe, but great danger in the deniall. <hi>He that will not belieue &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What of the Maſſe?</head>
               <p n="12">12. MAſſe is a compleate perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of that commaund; <hi>Do this in remembrance of me.</hi> Luc. 22. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by the Prieſt, prayers are ſaid for the whole Church, the holy Scripture is read, all the parts and ceremonies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of repreſent the life &amp; paſſion of Chriſt, who by meanes of thoſe words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in his name, <hi>Hoc est Corpus meum,</hi> is dayly offered in ſacrifice to the honour of God, &amp; profit of his Church. Whence it cometh to paſſe that fayth, gratitude, and loue towards our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is daily renewed; and the knowne prophecy of <hi>Malach. c.</hi> 1. fulfilled: <hi>From the riſing of the Sun vnto the going downe of the ſame, my Name is great among the Gentiles: and in euery place a pure oblation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15270:9"/>is ſacrificed and offered to my name,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the moſt ancient and common Tranſlation. Thus innumerable Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers conſtantly hold and practiſe, vpon ſufficient grounds, without the leaſt ſhew of impiety; why then, may I not ſecurely belieue I ſee not; nor how the denial can be free from danger, ſince vpon Disbelieuers only Damnation is denounced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What of Confeſsion &amp; Abſolution, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Sacrament of Pennance.</head>
               <p n="13">13. HEre a Chriſtian, after due exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of his Conſcience with harty ſorrow and purpoſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment (which acts are neceſſarily required) confeſſeth his ſinnes, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth abſolution by the miniſtery of the Prieſt. What danger can there be in this beliefe and practiſe? The Iewes charged Chriſt of blaſphemy, ſaying: <hi>Who can forgiue ſinnes but God?</hi> Againſt Chriſt they ſinned, becauſe they belieued him to be man only; which errour he chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by miracle. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9. giuing them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15270:9"/>withall to vnderſtand, that men alſo by power receiued from him, ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes; for in that they conceiued he taught, that man had power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes, he checked them not, but rather confirmed it: <hi>And that you may know</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) <hi>that the Sonne of Man hath authority in earth to forgiue ſinnes</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And the multitude glorifyed God who had giuen ſuch authority to men.</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer Chriſt to his Apoſtles Io. c. 22. ſayth: <hi>Receiue yee the holy Ghost, whoſe ſinns yee remit, they are remitted vnto them, and whoſe ſinnes yee retaine they are retayned:</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. <hi>Whatſoeuer yee shall bind on earth, shall be bound in heauen, and whatſoeuer yee shall looſe on earth, shall be looſed in heauen.</hi> Queſtionleſſe, the prime ſenſe of theſe words import a power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to men to forgiue ſinnes: nothing then is preſumptuouſly aſſumed by the Belieuers thereof; for though it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per only to God to forgiue ſinnes by his owne power and of himſelfe, yet the light of nature teacheth that man may alſo forgiue ſinnes by Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15270:10"/>him; as it is proper to a King only to forgiue Treaſons committed againſt his perſon, yet by Commiſſion &amp; his name a Subiect may haue power to do the ſame without iniury to the King, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the degree of a Subiect. Why may not the Miniſter of God by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him forgiue ſinne in his name without offending or exceeding the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of a dutifull creature? this is at the leaſt probable. In oppoſition I find no Scripture, but only admirations of a few dangers in compariſon of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuers; euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reaſon there can be none. Dangerous then is the deniall, Beliefe ſecure. <hi>Qui non crediderit;</hi> Who will not belieue ſhalbe damned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What of one Church, and one Head thereof?</head>
               <p n="14">14. IN Common Wealths throughout the world, I find an Vnity is moſt ſought for, and to that end one ſupreme gouernour and ruler; in one houſe one Maiſter, in one Towne one Maior, in one Company one Captaine, in one Army one Generall, in one Kingdome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15270:10"/>one King; can it beare any colour of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, to belieue that in the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Common-wealth, inſtituted by Chriſt, there is ordained one flock vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one Paſtour? <hi>Vt fiat vnum ouile, &amp; vnus paſtor.</hi> We ſee that in two ſupreme gouernements there is no mutuall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination, therefore not properly one; and where there are two Kings, it is ſufficient to conclude two Kingdomes. If then in Gods Church we admit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſupreme Gouernours, we cannot ſo perfectly call it one Church, as one flock is one vnder one Paſtor; which Chriſt promiſed ſhould be ſo. Whence it ſeemeth manifeſt, that for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of vnity in Gods Church one head is neceſſary, and that in the beliefe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is no danger, though there were no Scripture at all to warrant it. For as temporall Kings, though they haue no warrant for their ech particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar regall power out of holy Scripture, yet by law and iuſtice and conſcience we are iuſtly obliged, not to queſtion it: So I vnderſtand not, with what ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15270:11"/>a man may deny the authority of one ſupreme Gouernour of a Church ſo many hundred of yeares preſcribed. I need not heere heape vp texts of holy Scripture for proofe of the beliefe of one Church vnder one head, ſince in the beliefe thereof there is no ſhew of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, but in the deniall as much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of impiety, as in denying any Prince his due. Yet that it may appeare, that the deniers are not only in danger of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, but alſo of disbelieuing Chriſts words, I lay downe ſome few Texts to be pondered. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. <hi>Thou art Peter, &amp; vpon this rock will I build my Church, and the gates of Hel ſhall not preuaile against it.</hi> Behold one rock, one Church, &amp; that permanent againſt all aſſaults. <hi>Io.</hi> 21. to Peter he ſaid, <hi>feed my ſheepe;</hi> which words imply the full office of a Paſtor, that is, not only to prouide nouriſhment, but alſo to gouerne and defend, without which the office of a Shepheard is not complete. That alſo theſe words were ſpoken only to Peter, it is manifeſt by that thrice repeated interrogation of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15270:11"/>Chriſt, ſaying: <hi>Simon Peter, loueſt thou me?</hi> eſpecially when he addeth, <hi>more then thoſe?</hi> wherby he excluded the reſt of his Apoſtles; to which when <hi>S. Peter</hi> had anſwered that he loued him, Chriſt thereupon replyed, <hi>feed my ſheepe;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, the ſupreme dignity of Paſtorſhip and Vicegerency which I giue you, requireth greatioue and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, &amp; as you truly loue me, ſo be a true Paſtor in my Church; &amp; becauſe I giue you a dignity aboue the reſt whome you are to rule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my place, therfore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that your loue to me be ſingular.</p>
               <p n="15">15. This litle I haue obſerued, yeildeth ſuch probability at the leaſt, that it is manifeſt, it cannot without danger be denied, but that God his Church is one, vnder one head. But grant theſe places are not cleere in themſelues, yet the Common voyce of the world ſo long continued, expreſſed alſo in the two Creeds, may iuſtly excuſe any Belieuer from the leaſt danger of that ſentence <hi>Who will not belieue</hi> &amp;c. Securely then with the Apoſtles creed we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15270:12"/>
                  <hi>the holy Catholique Church:</hi> and with the Nicen, <hi>One, holy, Catholique, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolique Church:</hi> and not one, vnles it haue a ſupreme viſible Gouernour, to whom all are ſubordinate. What dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger can there be in this beliefe, if feare of God &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience only be regarded?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What concerning recommending our ſelues to the interceſsion of Saints.</head>
               <p n="16">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 16. TO iuſtify the beliefe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this point, it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that it is conformable to reaſon, and void of iniury to Chriſt. I aske then, why may not we commend our ſelues to the interceſſion of Saints, as well as <hi>S. Paul</hi> did commend himſelfe to the prayers of liuing Chriſtians? If it be anſwered, it is an iniury to Chriſt, who biddeth all come to him; I ſee not firſt how <hi>S. Paul</hi> can be excuſed, that oft commended himſelfe to the intetceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of inferiour Creatures, who ſhould haue gone to Chriſt only, and to no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy els. Looke what muſt be anſwered in excuſe of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> the ſame muſt iuſtify
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15270:12"/>our praying to Saints Moreouer, to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify <hi>S. Paul,</hi> and thoſe that commend themſelues to the interceſſion of Saints, it ſeemeth euident that both he and we go truly to Chriſt for we go not to Saints to giue vs this or that, but to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their mediation for fauours at God's hand; as truly we are ſaid to haue recourſe to the King for honour, if we deſire his Fauorits to intercede for vs: &amp; as notwithſtanding this mediation, we are truly ſaid not to wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the King, but to ſeeke to him; ſo by our interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Saints we wrong not Chriſt, but go to him; vnles a man ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not to ſeeke to Chriſt at all, but only to pray to Saints, which in no good Chriſtian can be imagined.</p>
               <p n="17">17. If it be anſwered, that Saints in heauen ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not heare vs; I aske, how can this be knowne? not by Scripture, ſince it witneſſeth that many Prophets ſaw obiects not only abſent, but not exiſtent many hundred yeares after their time, only by diuine inſpiration: nor by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for though were their hearing by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15270:13"/>corporal eares, there might be ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, yet ſince their hearing is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which is indifferent to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue obiects, as well abſent as preſent, this difficulty to any will appeare vaine and impertinent, ſince we know not, how our ſoule vnderſtands, nor how our eyes ſee, or eares heare.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Hence I gather, that the Belieuers of this Article though they had no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Scripture for proofe thereof, (which for the preſent I examine not) yet ſince their practice is conformable to reaſon, and conſequent to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> and the whole Church, they may reſt ſecure in the beliefe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the denyers bring ſome cleere places of holy Scripture to the contrary; ſuch places, I ſay, that need no explications, ſuppoſitions &amp;c. For theſe being but probabilities, are not ſufficient to make the Belieuers deny what before they belieued, leaſt perchance by not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing they proue guilty of damnation; from which they are doubtles free, though peraduenture the Saints heare
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15270:13"/>them not. As for iniury to Chriſt, I haue ſhewed before, there is not the leaſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What Choice may be ſecurely made concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the making, and worſhipping the Image of Christ, and his Saints?</head>
               <p n="19">19. FOr the end of a ſafe reſolution in this point, it is neceſſary firſt to declare, what kind of worſhip is pretended due to Images; and for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, I will diſcourſe of the Image of Chriſt crucifyed, whereby what may be ſaid of the reſt with proportion, it will eaſily appeare.</p>
               <p n="20">20. The worſhip then pretended, neuer tendeth to the Image, out of an apprehenſion of any Diuinity therein contained, but only out of a faith in Chriſt repreſented by that Image, that is, belieuing Chriſt worthy of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, repreſented by this picture, in manner as he viſibly once appeared. Whence euident it is firſt, that by ſuch worſhip Chriſt is immediatly worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Secondly, that no honour due to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15270:14"/>God, is transferred to a Creature. Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly, that whatſoeuer honour exteriour or interiour te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth towards the Image, is not for it, nor reſteth there, but by our faith and interiour reuerence, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to Chriſt, for whom &amp; to whom it is exhibited: for ſince perfect worſhip conſiſteth both in the exteriour and interiour acts conioyned, the interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our giuing life, &amp; the very being wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to the exteriour, the interiour reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting Chriſt for himſelfe, and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage only for Chriſt; no ſigne of iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Chriſt can be imagined. Or in a word, the worſhip heere in queſtion is only an outward honour towards the Image, proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an inward reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Chriſt himſelfe. And as <hi>S. Mary Magdalen</hi> worſhiped Chriſt as a man out of beliefe of the Diuinity contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in him, or rather as ſome worſhip their Communion for the Connexion it hath with Chriſt, whom it repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth; ſo in like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner the worſhip giuen to Images, is for the Connexion they haue with Chriſt himſelfe. The queſtion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15270:14"/>then is, whether the worſhip thus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood be lawfull or no?</p>
               <p n="21">21. According to the new tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Bible, the negatiue part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Belieuers ſeemes iuſtified. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. expreſly forbidding the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and worſhipping of any Image whatſoeuer. But the firſt doubt that heere occurreth, and that a maine one, is; how this latter tranſlation can be iuſtified, reading, <hi>Image,</hi> againſt the ancient, <hi>Idol,</hi> or <hi>grauen thing,</hi> and ſo interpreted by ancient Doctours, and Fathers. Secondly, grant <hi>Image,</hi> the right tranſlation, how can we be ſure, that the ſame law is now in force, more then the law of the Saboth or Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion? I ſee not how theſe two doubts can be ſolued by cleer Scripture which is neceſſary to repeale an anciently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued beliefe in a Church.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Moreouer, admitting the word <hi>Image,</hi> and the Law to ſtand; it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that place proueth nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the worſhip of Images as expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated before, but only againſt Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15270:15"/>abuſe of them.</p>
               <p n="23">23. Firſt, out of the end of the Law, which was, that the honour of God ſhould bee inuiolably kept, by giuing diuine worſhip to him, and to no Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature; therefore in the beginning it is ſaid; <hi>I am thy Lord God, thou ſhalt haue no other Gods but me:</hi> and after he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that no Idols, nor other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes of any thing ſhould be made, he added the cauſe: <hi>For I am thy Lord God; a iealous God;</hi> that is, make not to thy ſelfe any Idol or Image for thy God, for I am thy God. Where marke, that particle, <hi>for,</hi> which giueth a reaſon, why he doth forbid <hi>Images;</hi> becauſe he was their God, and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ealous God: which reaſon muſt ſuppoſe ſuch a vſe of Images as ſhould transferre Gods honour from him to them; els that particle, <hi>for,</hi> is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, if due honour of Images may conſiſt with the honour due to God; as that before declared doth, and I will ſhew more hereafter.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Secondly, becauſe, if that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand haue force now againſt worſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15270:15"/>it is likewiſe of force againſt all making of Images, in ſo much that the very Kings coyne muſt be proued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull: but this is palpably abſurd, therefore alſo abſurd, that the Law ſhold now be of force againſt all Image worſhip. The firſt propoſition is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: for what the Law forbiddeth to be worſhiped, it alſo forbiddeth to be made; or if it forbiddeth them not to be made, how doth it forbid them to be worſhiped? the law expreſly ſayth; <hi>theu ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe, nor worſhip.</hi> If any reply, that thoſe firſt words, <hi>thou shalt not make to thy ſelfe &amp;c.</hi> ſignify <hi>thou shalt not make to worſhip,</hi> intimating that the worſhip only, and not the making of Images is forbidden; I aske him firſt, how he can proue this his interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Scripture? If he cannot, I may not without danger receiue, or make any Image. Secondly it is manifeſt that, that interpretation can haue no grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in Scripture, vnles we alſo ſay, that when <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.4. it is ſaid, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> made themſelues, or to themſelues
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15270:16"/>
                  <hi>Aprons;</hi> and <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Make thee,</hi> or to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe, <hi>an Arke:</hi> &amp; <hi>Num.</hi> 10. <hi>Make thee,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to thy ſelfe, <hi>two trumpets,</hi> is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of worſhip. Thirdly, if the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part, <hi>thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe,</hi> be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, <hi>thou ſhalt not make to worship</hi> why ſhould it be added, <hi>and thou sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not worship?</hi> If then we vnderſtand thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place to be of force againſt Image wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, we muſt conclude it to be of forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the making, and receauing of all manner of Images, which Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelfe reproueth, commanding Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſars coyne to be giuen to him. Whence it being manifeſt, that the ſecond pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is true, to wit, that this is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, it followeth euidently that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo abſurd to ſay, that the law is now i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> force againſt Image worſhip.</p>
               <p n="25">25. A third and chiefe reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue cleere warrant out of holy Scripture, both for the making &amp; worſhiping of Images; the ſame Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker commanding Cherubims ouer the Arke <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. and a Serpent of braſſe <hi>Num.</hi> 21. Cherubims, Lyons <hi>Reg</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15270:16"/>6.7. to be made; how can this ſtand with a total prohibtion of Images? That Arke repreſented God not ſo properly as the Image of Chriſt repreſenteth Chriſt, yet <hi>Dauid</hi> teacheth vs, <hi>Adore the footſtoole of our Lord, for he is holy:</hi> which he ſayth not, out of any Command there euer was of adoring the Arke, ſince there was none; but only out of Conſideration, that it repreſenteth in ſome ſort the Maieſty of God. <hi>Ioſuac.</hi> 7. fell <hi>prostrate before the Arke:</hi> where I ſee not, what he did more or leſſe then is required in the worſhip of Images: did <hi>Ioſua</hi> then breake God's command? We read <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Nu.</hi> 22. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 5.14. and els where, how the holy Prophets adored God in Images, or in Angels repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his perſon, proſtrating themſelues before them: and though their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was directed to God, yet their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip was directed to thoſe ſenſible apparitions, or Images repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting God to their imaginations; wherein they conceiued God as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and theſe Images repreſenting
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15270:17"/>God, morally one obiect; in the ſame manner as it hapneth in the honour of Images, and in the worſhip of the figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue Communion, or as all Ciuill Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do, when they honour the <hi>Chayre of State,</hi> or <hi>Preſence Chamber</hi> of a King, without wrong to Chriſt, or to the King.</p>
               <p n="26">26. Theſe three arguments do mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſhew, that whether in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment we read <hi>Idol,</hi> or <hi>Image;</hi> by it nothing can be proued, againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared manner of worſhiping Images, vnleſſe we will proue a Contradiction in holy Scripture. Moreouer ſince it is cleerly proued, by thoſe examples and practice taken out of holy Scripture, that in ſuch worſhip there is no ſigne of dishonour to God; it is doubtles more ſecure with the common practice of the world, to honour them, then by the deniall of it to condemne ſuch mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt authority.</p>
               <p n="27">27. That in the refuſing there is no ſecurity, it is alſo manifeſt, ſince the Scripture brought is not cleere for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15270:17"/>of Image-worſhip, therfore not ſufficient to cry downe an ancient practice, proued by ſound Texts of Scripture, which can neuer be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with thoſe words of the Law, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe where <hi>Image</hi> is read, we reade <hi>Idol:</hi> which word ſignifieth a Comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that no Creature ſhould be made, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped as God. This vſe of Images de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared is iuſtified both in reſpect of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and worſhiping, by other texts of Scripture without any Contradiction to thoſe words of the Law; when the contrary without any neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth a man to deny cleere reaſon and Scripture.</p>
               <p n="28">28. It may be obiected; that ſince Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry hath been begun and maintained by Images, and ſince men are prone to forget God, and apply themſelues who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to corporall obiects, the ſecure way is to abandon Images, at the leaſt in Churches. This is ſpoken without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or law; Without law, for there can be none brought, ſince not <hi>Images,</hi> but <hi>Idols</hi> were the beginning and maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15270:18"/>of Idolatry. Images I haue proued warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table in holy Scripture. Without reaſon: for, whereas an Idol repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing beſides it ſelfe, and ſo is worſhiped, an Image repreſenteth a true thing, therefore moueth a man to a reuerence proportionable to the obiect repreſented Whence in reaſon an <hi>Idol</hi> occaſioneth Idolatry not repreſenting any further obiect whither our thoghts and honour may be transferred; when contrarywiſe an <hi>Image</hi> of a true obiect neceſſarily draweth our minds, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to ſome thing beſides it ſelfe: ſo that aske any ſimple Belieuer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he pray to an Image, or put any Confidence in it, he will ſay no; aske him againe, when he is kneeling before a picture with his eyes fixed on it, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he directs his prayers? he will ſay to Chriſt, or ſome Saint. What hurt is there in this? <hi>S. Mary Magdelen</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, kiſſed and bathed with her teares the feet of Chriſt: what iuſtified that act, but the vnion which thoſe ſacred feet had with his diuinity, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15270:18"/>ſhe ſaw not, but appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by fayth? Though betweene Chriſt and his picture there be not ſo immediate connexion, yet a morall Connexion there is, ſuch as betweene the King, and his Picture, Chayre of ſtate, Embaſſadour &amp;c. why then may not a Chriſtian apprehend this conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion betweene Chriſt and his Image repreſenting him, and accordingly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite due honour, without danger of Idolatry?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Whether is holy Scripture, the only Rule of our Faith?</head>
               <p n="29">29. HIther to I haue ſhewed, that ſuppoſing Scripture the only rule, beleefe is more ſecure, then deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; for both parties relying vpon the ſame Scripture, can neuer conuince ech others interpretation of falſity, as experience ſufficiently ſheweth, and probability at leaſt muſt be ſuppoſed on both parts; in which caſe finding no further euidence, prudence compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth me to chooſe that part which is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15270:19"/>moſt remote from danger of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: <hi>Who will not betieue, ſhall be damned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30. Now, that there may remayne no doubt at all, of the ſecure Choice of beliefe; I will ſhew it conſequent to reaſon, &amp; holy Scripture, that we muſt admit of ſome other rule beſides Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If then beliefe be grounded not only vpon probable authority of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (wherin it is equal at the leaſt with authority of Deniers or Disbelieuers) but alſo vpon an other rule apparently knowne and ſeene, as it is fit for a rule to be, there can be no doubt of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of beleefe.</p>
               <p n="31">31. And firſt, I ſuppoſe it is more then probable, or either Phyſically cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that there hath euer beene a Church, teaching and practizing thoſe points of beliefe aforementioned, not ſufficiently diſproued in point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance &amp; incorruption in Doctrine, though the gates of Hell haue breathed forth all malice againſt it.</p>
               <p n="32">32. Secondly, I ſuppoſe holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15270:19"/>as inſpired by the holy Ghoſt to be a certaine rule of Chriſtian beliefe; yet for that it is certaine that al is not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that was deliuered by Chriſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it any where ſay, that it is the infallible and ſole word of God, and for that it is obſcure, &amp; doth not cleerly explicate it ſelfe, as it is manifeſt by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; it can not be an infallible rule for the deciding of contradictory opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions drawne from the ſame, though it alone may be a ſufficient direction to let vs know what more ſecurely may be belieued.</p>
               <p n="33">33. The queſtion then is: Whether beſides the Scripture, a <hi>Church</hi> alſo, as an vnpartiall Interpreter thereof, be to be admitted; which is as much to ſay: Whether the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voice of a <hi>Church</hi> interpreting holy Scripture, be a more ſecure rule, then the voice of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men, whoſe priuate interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as before I ſhewed, are not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine proofes out of holy Scripture, but only probabilityes out of their owne iudgment: which notwithſtanding,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15270:20"/>ſome will oblige all to admit as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and contemne the explication of an ancient Church.</p>
               <p n="34">34. For the negatiue part I find no cleere Scripture, but ſuch texts as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire hard interpretation, and which as much oppoſe the practice of the firſt Primitiue Church, then admitted as a doubtles rule, as it will appeare to any that ſhall conſider them: <hi>You ſhall not ad a word. Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Search the Scriptures. Ioan.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Theſe things are written that you may belieue. Io.</hi> 20.31. <hi>All Scripture diuinely inſpired is profitable.</hi> Are not theſe places of as much force againſt the Primitiue Church? Do they &amp; the like ſay, that all truth is written? or that what is written is diuine Scripture? or that it needs no helpe of interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no not of a Church but of priuate ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits? What ground then doth there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for the inforcing of ſole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as the only rule of our beliefe?</p>
               <p n="35">35. For the affirmatiue part, we haue firſt, that Article of the Apoſtles Creed: <hi>I belieue the holy Catholique Church:</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:15270:20"/>How can we belieue the Church of Chriſt to be holy and Catholique, and doubt of Gods protection of it in point of true beliefe and Doctrine?</p>
               <p n="36">36. Secondly, the authority of the Euangeliſts: <hi>Math. vlt. Teach all Nations</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold I am with you euery day euen to the conſummation of the world. Math.</hi> 18.17. <hi>If he shall not heare the Church, let him be to thee as a heathen &amp; publica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Luc.</hi> 10.16. <hi>he that heareth you heareth me, and he that contemneth you contemneth me.</hi> Beſides, the Church is called, the <hi>Pillar and firmament of truth. Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Light of the world. Math.</hi> 5.14. Do not theſe texts probably point at a liuing rule?</p>
               <p n="37">37. Thirdly, ſince Chriſt obligeth vs to a beliefe of his doctrine vnder paine of damnation, it is manifeſt that by ſome meanes he will make it appeare vnto vs; but by Scripture alone it doth not ſufficiently appeare, for by it we know not what is Scripture, nor which is the true ſenſe of Scripture, els all would ſoone agree: therefore Scripture is not ſufficient alone to deliuer vnto
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15270:21"/>vs our ſauing fayth. But the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted and indifferent Interpreter thereof is an vniuerſall Church; ſo as we may ſecurely be ruled by it, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the ſaid Scripture, and cannot be reiected without danger of disbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God's word.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Grant to disbelieuers probability of reaſon, yet their danger is certaine.</head>
               <p n="38">38. SOme may thinke, that this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe proueth Belieuers ſecure, but not that Dis belieuers are in certaine danger, if they be ruled according to the meanes and capacity God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them, and that ſuch are not ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne Deniers of truth, conſequently ſecure inough. I grant, that inuincible ignorance may excuſe Disbelieuers, as ſuch, from ſinne; yet it followeth not that continuall and finall disbeliefe (though inuincible) can conſiſt with grace neceſſary to Saluation: but this I diſpute not, nor againſt theſe, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as do, or may diſcern a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene beliefe &amp; disbeliefe;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15270:21"/>and who may ſee that the grounds of beliefe are at leaſt probable, &amp; the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice harmeles; who finally know dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be denounced vpon disbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: notwithſtanding aduenture vpon the denying part, moued only by the ſame reaſons, which they muſt ſuppoſe in confeſſed Heretiques. Let any one define what disbelieuer may be guilty of damnation, he ſhall find thereby, that either he ſhall condemne theſe Disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuers I ſpeake of, or els conclude that there neuer haue been any.</p>
               <p n="39">39. Some againe may ſay, if the beliefe be ſuppoſed only probably true, then the denial is alſo ſuppoſed probable. I ſuppoſe neither probability in the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue part, nor only probability in the beliefe; but ſhunning this diſpute as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, only out of the vndeniable proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility for the beliefe, and the ſecurity therof, I conuince the danger of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial.</p>
               <p n="40">40. But it may be replyed, that at leaſt the Disbelieuer by this Diſcourſe, iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the beliefe but probable, may alſo
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15270:22"/>iudge his owne probable, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently his danger alſo but probable. I anſwer, that notwithſtanding the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belieuer thinke his opinion probable, he cannot iudge his danger only probable. For as probability in the Belieuer, where no hurt appeares, freeth him certainly from danger; ſo the probability only, which the Disbeliener ſuppoſeth, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him in certaine danger of disbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing what Chriſt hath reuealed: firſt, becauſe his danger is certaine in the ſame degree as the beliefe is probable; but the beliefe is certainly probable at the leaſt in reſpect of the great authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the belieuers; therfore the Disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuers danger is alſo certaine, though he conceiue a probability of his disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. Secondly, becauſe the disbeliefe is as certainly da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous, as it is certainly not euident (and more euidence is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to free the disbeliefe from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then is neceſſary to free the beliefe; this, though it were too much, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning no hurt) but the Dis-belieuers do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is certainly not euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, therefore
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15270:22"/>it is certainly dangerous. The firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is cleere, for if there be not eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency for the disbeliefe the contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen may be true, conſequently obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to beliefe. The ſecond Propoſition, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the Disbelieuers doctrine is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ident, appeareth by the nouelty, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſtancy, diſagreements, and other circumſtances incident to it; as alſo by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ouerſwaying authority of the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers who want not any thing neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y required to a probability at leaſt, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y reflexion any one may obſerue; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>her can the want of euidency, in the Articles denied, warrant the Disbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers; els who could belieue? or rather who could be charged of hereſy? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he laſt Conſequence of the Reply is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alſe, for thogh to ſome their disbeliefe nay ſeeme probable, out of a probable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udgment, that Chriſt deliuered not ſuch words, or in ſuch a ſenſe; yet their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anger is certaine, becauſe the contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eliefe is certainly probable at leaſt, which may conuince them, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaue the ſecure beliefe, wherein there
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15270:23"/>can be no danger, and chooſe that p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whereon Chriſt's denunciation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fall. Nor may this argument be retort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt Belieuers though their doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be ſuppoſed but probable, becauſe their Beliefe there is contayned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> harme or danger as in the disbelieue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and danger knowne breedeth an ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of further inquiry, &amp; remoue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all ignorance which only can excuſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in beliefe.</p>
               <p n="51">51. Againe it may be replyed, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this hindereth not, but that Disbel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers may conceiue their disbeliefe pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, conſequently at leaſt not impu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſinne, and therefore free fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> danger. I anſwere, that if a man co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his disbeliefe probable, he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon iuſtly to doubt, eſpecially if h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> probability ariſe out of apprehenſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of probability in the contrary belie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which alone maketh the disbeliefe da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous in practice: as if a man ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> probably thinke Baptiſme not neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for infants, he may not neglect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſince in this the danger is apparent: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:15270:23"/>caſe inuincibly he conceiue his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on true, I medle not, as impertinent this purpoſe, and a metaphyſicall caſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mongſt vnderſtanding men.</p>
               <p n="52">52. If it be asked, what degree of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ability Belieuers may be conceiued to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue? I anſwer, that as great as can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or any thing. They haue Scripture, Tradition, Conſent of Nations, reaſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euer cleerely diſproued as it is euident; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ince in numerable dayly anſwer all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ections made againſt them: or let any body ſet downe what is ſufficient to make an opinion apparently probable, that he ſhall cleerly finde in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Belieuers.</p>
               <p n="53">53. But Disbelieuers will ſay, that they belieue in God's word, and deny only what they find not contayned in it. This is not in queſtion; and who will not belieue God's word? The Diuels (as <hi>S. Iames</hi> witneſſeth) belieue and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: the queſtion is, whether they disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue nothing, or by their denials put not themſelues in danger of denying what is ſufficiently deliuered as God's
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15270:24"/>word, forging or reiecting it accord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Touchſtone of their fancy. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it in queſtion, whether what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mighty God hath reuealed in Script<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought to be belieued; but what God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reuealed: and this is not only the wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word, but the ſenſe, which we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, not perfectly from the bare lette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but by the helpe of prudent rule which to reiect is dangerous, eſpecial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on their part that deny Articles prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deliuered.</p>
               <p n="54">54. In Concluſion of this Chapter, will anſwere one obiection, by man eſteemed a ſecure <hi>Quietus est;</hi> They ſay God obligeth not men to impoſſibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ties: ſince then at leaſt the vulgar ſort o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> people cannot diſcerne thoſe differe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein learned men do diſagree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ech one may ſecurely reſt in that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he is taught, belieuing the Cree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. This Diſcourſe ſuppoſeth holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture the only rule of beliefe: about th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true ſenſe whereof, ſince it is euiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> learned men do not agree, and no pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man can be Iudge betweene theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15270:24"/>differences, it is manifeſt that who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeth only vpon Scripture, cannot be ſecure that his disbeliefe is true, or that he refuſe not to belieue what he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to belieue vnder paine of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. To ſay, that euery one may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely belieue according as he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands, is but a deſperate ſhift and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth an impoſſibility of any hereſie. The obiection then conuinceth the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a Church as a liuing rule; for God obligeth vs not to impoſſibilities; but it is impoſſible for any to diſcerne the monſtrous differences of priuate mens interpretations of God's word: Therefore he obligeth not to the beliefe of his word vpon theſe priuate inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations: But he obligeth vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue; therfore by ſome other way then by Scripture alone, he maketh it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: this can be no other but the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15270:25"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p n="55">55. THus I haue ſufficiently ſhewed the ſecurity of belieuers, exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifyed in a few Articles moſt in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, contayning no harme, nor oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to any knowne Law of God, as the better part of the Chriſtian world euer hath witneſſed, but at leaſt moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conformable to Chriſts expreſſe word: I ſee not what part of this can be doubted.</p>
               <p>Conſequently to this, I haue alſo ſhewed in what manifeſt danger Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belieuers are: firſt by reiecting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the authority of an ancient Church, &amp; the only knowne Church when Luther began this denying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, confeſſed to haue been the true Church, and as yet not conuicted of corruption in fayth, nor as much as charged by any greater authority then it ſelfe: Let them take heed, that be not ſpoken of them, <hi>He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me: Who will not heare the Church let him be reputed as a Heathen and Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can.</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:15270:25"/>Secondly, by chooſing the disbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing part, out of ſeeming reaſons, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing themſelues to needles dangers of that ſentence: <hi>Who will not belieue &amp;c.</hi> For if the contrary beliefe muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed probable, as vndoubtedly it muſt, then the disbeliefe may with probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be a deniall of Chriſt's word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently may be, it deſerueth damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; this is euident to reaſon, and no iudicious man can deny it.</p>
               <p>If any feare, that as disbeliefe of what Chriſt deliuered maketh him a lyer, ſo alſo beliefe of what he deliuered not; let them but obſerue the diſparity bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene Belieuers &amp; Disbelieuers; thoſe deny what Chriſt deliuered as manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly as he deliuered other truths: But Belieuers vpon the ſame grounds that moue them to beliefe of other articles, ſuppoſe the points controuerted deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by Chriſt, which if they were not deliuered they are only guilty of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, not of making Chriſt a lyer.</p>
               <p>Who then ſeeth not how much it concerneth a Chriſtian not raſhly to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15270:26"/>deny what anciently is deliuered by the Church? On true beliefe God's fauour dependeth, on this our eternall welfare. We expect but one death, one irreuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable iudgment, one Eternity of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynes or miſery. This is promiſed to Disbeliefe, that to true Belieuers. Shall a Chriſtian aduenture vpon ſeeming probabilities, and leaue ſecurity? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe is ſecure, voyd of harme; to Disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuers it is ſaid: <hi>Who will not belieue, ſhall be damned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let then all Disbelieuers examine their Disbeliefe, and harken to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of <hi>S. Auguſtin. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ. Grauiter peccat, qui in rebus ad ſalutem animae pertinentibus, certis incerta praeponit.</hi> Heauy is his ſinne, who in matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſafety of his ſoule, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vncertaine meanes before cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15270:26"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS of this Diſcourſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THe Preface.</hi> pag. 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What choice ought a man to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Reall Preſence of Christs bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud in the Sacrament of the laſt Supper.</hi> pag. 11.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What of the Maſſe.</hi> pag. 15.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What of Confeſsion and Abſolution, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Sacrament of Pennance.</hi> pag. 16.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What of the Church, and one Head therof.</hi> pag. 18.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15270:27"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>What concerning the recommending our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to the interceſsion of Saintes.</hi> pag. 22</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What choice may be ſecurely made, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the making and worſhipping the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Christ &amp; his Saintes.</hi> pag. 25.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whether is Holy Scripture the only Rule of our fayth.</hi> pag. 35.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grant to Disbelieuers probability of Reaſon, yet their danger is certaine.</hi> pag. 40.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Concluſion.</hi> pag. 48.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15270:27"/>
            <p>THE CONVICTION OF NOVELTIE, AND DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of antiquitie.</p>
            <p>OR DEMONSTRATIVE ARGVMENTS of the falſitie of the newe Religion of England: And trueth of the Catholike Roman faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DELIVERED IN TWELVE PRINCIPAL Sylogiſmes, and directed to the more ſcholaſticall wits of the Realme of great Britanie, eſpecially to the ingenious ſtudents of the two moſt renowned vniuerſities of Oxford &amp; Cambrige.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AVTHOR R. B. Roman Catholike, and one of the English, Clergie, and Miſſion.</p>
            <p>—<hi>GRATIAS AGO DEO MEO PER IESVM CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum pro omnibus vobis quia fides veſtra annuntiatur in vniuerſo mundo.</hi> Rom. 1.6.</p>
            <p>QVISQVIS ES ASSERTOR NOVORVM Dogmatum queſo te vt parcas Romanis auribus, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas fidei quae ab Apoſtolico ore laudata eſt. <hi>S. Hier. ep ad Pamachium &amp; Oceanum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CATVAPOLI, Apud viduam MARCI WYONIS.</p>
            <p>Anno M.DC.XXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
